After the informal examples,
let's discuss the formal definition
of Petri
nets this week.
Now this looks like
a complicated definition at first.
But it
simply uses set-theoretic
terms that I repeated
in a video last week.
Or that you should already
know from somewhere else, maybe
also from
recent mathematics lectures.
So here
is mathematically stated:
A Petri net from now on, if we
want to represent it formally/mathematically (and ultimately the
syntax of the Petri net independent of
the graphical representation), is defined like this.
As
a 5-tuple.
Five components
play into this.
We have a finite,
non-empty set of places.
Non-empty because a Petri net
without places would make no sense.
And finite, because we are
only considering finite Petri nets.
Although I have
said that the behavior
described by this
could still be infinite.
So a corresponding flat state
diagram could be infinite, even
though the Petri net
has only finitely many places.
This is because, as we have already
seen in an example in an earlier video,
it could be that an arbitrary
number of tokens accumulate on a site.
So then the total number of
all possible state configurations is quite
infinite, because of these arbitrarily
many tokens on one place,
even though the Petri net itself has
finitely many places and finitely many transitions.
So S is such a
set (finite, nonempty) of places.
Analogously, a set T (also
finite, and also non-empty) of transitions.
In the graphical representation, these are
the empty, large circles and rectangles.
So that's part
of the structural information.
Of course, we need to
know more, namely about the arrows/connections.
They are represented here in the
mathematical definition by two such functions.
These are in each
case functions from the set
of places to the
natural numbers including the zero.
And such two functions
exist for each transition t.
So for each transition t, each element of
this set T, there are two such functions.
And they're
called this here:
Bullet, filled circle, before
t and after t.
But these are just names,
just a short notation for them.
We actually want to express the precondition
weights of t and postcondition weights of t.
We want to do this
for each transition and each place.
We take a transition t
and specify a function that
assigns a natural
number to each place.
Namely, this specifies how many
tokens are taken out of each
place by
this transition t.
Or, if we consider
this function, then how many
tokens are put on a given
place by the corresponding transition t.
Since a value is
given here for each place.
Because this is a function from the set
of places into the set of natural numbers.
Thus always all
places are considered.
For really every place
a value is given.
That is the
concept of the function.
But we can also have zero
as a result for a certain place.
Then there is
another such function.
Again, a function of
places into the natural numbers.
And that is
the initial marking.
This has per se nothing
to do with the transitions, but
describes how in the initial situation of
the Petri net the tokens are distributed.
Therefore, besides the sets S and T and
these families of functions (which specify such a
function for each t out of T),
there is another distinguished function here, namely m0.
This is the initial
marking or start marking.
And, as
I said before:
Such an expression, that is,
one of these bullet t
or t-bullet functions, evaluated for a
particular location s, is called a weight.
Or pre-weight in that case,
post-weight in the other case.
These functions of this shape S
to N, which occur here several
times, are also
generally called "markings".
Here it already appears as
a term in the name.
But also these functions
can be understood as markings.
We will need this term, so
I will define it again separately.
So a marking is simply
a function of this form.
And it can indicate how many
tokens are currently in individual places.
That would be the application here,
to indicate the initial or initial marking.
But such a function can just
also be used to indicate how
many tokens are to
be taken from individual places.
This was the
case for the pre-weight.
Or how many tokens are
to be added to individual places.
That would be the
case for the post-weighting.
And, of course, it's important to note that there
can be variance in each of the three cases.
So it can be assigned here, in
a marking, a different value for each place.
Now we won't always necessarily write
these functions down as functions, that
is, with
an assignment rule.
If S is small, for example
contains only 3 or 4 elements,
we actually want to
specify only three values.
Then we will often write
them in tuple notation again.
So in particular, if we have places s_1
through s_n, for a not-too-large n, and we've decided
on an order (perhaps
numbering the places from
s_1 to, say, s_4), then we
can also express/write such a function by
simply writing down the results of m,
from that function, for s_1 through s_n.
We'll see that in an example in a
moment, in case this seems obscure to you.
And
of course:
This mathematical notation, using this
term, will ultimately have to
be brought into agreement with
the graphical representation, of course.
We've already seen the graphical representation, with
the places and rectangles and so on.
There will be the relation
that the places from the mathematical
definition also correspond to the places
, the circles, in the graphic representation.
And the transitions
from the mathematical definition,
the elements of T, will
be represented as rectangles or squares.
The tokens, that is, what
is described by the initial
marking, are represented as filled small
circles lying on the large circles.
Edges between places and
transitions are represented with arrows.
This is the information that lies in
the mathematical representation in the weight functions.
And a key point that makes
the graphical representation perhaps more intuitive
than the mathematical representation is that in
special cases we can save information for
the weight functions in the
graphical representation, or leave it implicit.
So we won't draw arrows
in the graphical representation if
the weight
functions say,
for example, that a connection from a
place to a transition has weight 0.
Then the edge
will be omitted altogether.
And if a weight is
1, we will just draw an
arrow, but not
give it a value.
In the example from the last
video, on the other hand, where we
once wrote a 2 to an arrow
or did so in two places, this
would correspond to cases where such a function would
also sometimes have a value 2 as a result.
So we have to
interpret the graphical representation
relative to
the mathematical representation.
I will now do
this directly with an example.
Let's take this
graphically represented Petri net.
This obviously has
three places, three transitions,
and at the beginning the
tokens are distributed as shown here.
And there's
a transition that
generates two tokens as in the last
video when the transition t1 is fired.
That would be
the graphical representation.
In order to
write down a mathematical
representation, we have to
decide on a place order.
Here it is obvious to give the
places just in the order s1, s2, s3.
We will need this if we
want to describe the markings as tuples.
Mathematically, we would have here
a three-element set of places,
a three-element set
of transitions, and
the transitions can be written down,
for example, for t1 as follows.
What do we know about
this transition from the graphical representation?
We know that it consumes
a token from s1, consumes
a token from s2, and puts two tokens into
s3, but does not take a token from s3.
The precondition
function says:
One token from s1, one token
from s2, and zero tokens from s3.
This corresponds to the non-existent
arrow from here to here.
And the fact that
t1 deposits something exactly in
s3, two tokens,
is expressed here.
Nothing is deposited in s1 because
there is no back arrow here.
Nothing is placed in s2 because
there is no back arrow here either.
Two tokens are
stored in s3.
This information, in these
two lines, corresponds to
the information given here by the
corresponding arrows and the labels around t1.
The same would be done for t2
and t3, thus writing down corresponding additional lines.
For the initial marking, that is, for
the distribution of tokens in the initial image,
we have this start
marking or initial marking.
It
says:
On s1 there has to
be one token on s2 there
have to be two tokens and s3
has to be empty at the beginning.
If we decide
on an order of the
places (s1, s2, s3 for example), then
we can write this information more compactly.
For example, we simply write down
the precondition function for t1 in the
form that we form a triple from
the three results for s1, s2, s3.
For this we just
need to know this order.
So if we were
to write them down the
other way around, we might
have to put the zero here.
But for s1, s2, s3, we have 1,
1, 0 here and 0, 0, 2 here.
Of course, we can
do the same thing for
the initial marking and
specify that this way.
And if we do that for t2, t3
as well, we would have a mathematical representation
exactly corresponding to the graphical representation,
which we can just work with mathematically.
We will want to specify Petri nets
sometimes this way and sometimes that way.
Depending on the intended use,
we may want to define
something more mathematically, perform analysis
for the Petri nets, for example.
Or do we
want to illustrate or
simulate rather, or intuitively go through
and discuss what transitions are possible?
Then we can work
more with the graphical representation.
But you must know both representations
and also be able to relate them.